בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is פ"ט. Pei Tes. Oh look at that, the
דף, daf, the last letter corresponds to the day of the עומר,
Omer, but that's not going to last long. Okay, maybe it will
though. I mean it will if you do plus one. What? No,
but when we get to צ"א Tzadi Aleph it'll be day eleven
or something, so it's a good way to remember the day of
the עומר, Omer, just occurs to me. Okay anyway, we pick up
three lines from the top and we're continuing to look at the
משנה Mishna about the way in which a person deals with handling
accurate measures, which doesn't only mean that their measures themselves are not
inaccurate, but that they clean out their measuring cups or their
measuring vessels, that they wipe down their measures, they wipe down the
scales, and also when you're actually transferring the pouring it into the
or weighing it, the act of the weighing itself, do you throw
in a little bit extra, do you make the scales tip a
little bit in favor of the buyer, and so on when you
fill up a container, do you do it level or do you
do a mount, ways in which you ensure that the buyer is
not getting undersold. Okay so let's take a look. So the משנה
Mishna says: מקום שנהגו למוד בגסה אל ימוד בדקה, Makom shenahagu lamod
begasa al yimod bedaka,
that if you normally use a large measure when you sell you
shouldn't use a small measure and the reverse, and a place in
which they normally sort of do a little curve at the top,
a meniscus, then you shouldn't do it flat and when you do
it flat you shouldn't do the meniscus. So we understand why if
you normally do the little curve at the top you shouldn't do
it flat because then you're giving the buyer less than is the
practice to give the buyer, you usually give the buyer that little
extra and now you're just doing a flat measure. And the same,
now what's the issue about the small and the big measure? Well,
if you are with each measuring, since you can never be exactly
precise, presumably even if you're doing flat, you'll never be exactly precise,
there's always going to be a little tipping, a little bit of
an error and you're always going to want to make that error
on the side of the buyer. So if you do multiple measurements,
if you measure with a lot of small containers, the buyer is
going to get more because in each measuring there's going to be
a little bit of error in his favor. So therefore, if the
place is, he loses out when you use one large measure rather
than if you measure multiple times in small. So you understand why
you don't want to sort of do it in a way that's
going to hurt the buyer. But the interesting part of the משנה
Mishna is if the practice is the other way, you don't want
to do it in the reverse which will hurt the seller. We
care about the seller as well, although you would think it's the
initiative of the seller to decide how he's going to measure it
out, but I don't know, let's say the buyer says I
actually want to buy, I want to use these measures as opposed
to those measures. So it's clear you follow the conventions.
So even with these conventions, even if it's a place that you
do a flat measure and whatever, there still is, I want to
make it clear, the first point of the משנה, Mishna, that there
has to be some thing extra you give the buyer just to
be safe. So even if it's a flat measure and so on,
you're still going to throw in a little extra.
But it's different than the act of measuring, right? Is the act
of measuring balanced and then you're throwing in an extra apple or
is the act of measuring imbalanced in the same way with when
you're doing a
volume filling up a volume. לפנים משורת
הדין.
lifnim mishurat
hadin.
Right, לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, that's a שידוך, shidduch, so
it's right exactly. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מנין שאין מוחקין במקום שגודשין
ואין גודשין במקום שמוחקין? Minayin she'ein mokechin bemakom shegodshin ve'ein godshin bemakom
shemokechin? How do you know that you do not smooth the top
of this when you're doing a volume measure in the place that
normally they do a heap and that you don't do a heap
in the place that they do the smoothing? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar:
איפה שלמה. Eifa shleima. This is the פסוק: pasuk: איפה שלמה וצדק
יהיה לך. Eifa shleima vetzedek yihyeh lach. Okay, so it has to
be whole, whole means whole presumably according to the norms of the
place. So if it's normally heaped and it's flat that's not whole,
if it's normally flat and it's heaped it's also more than whole,
so it's also not a complete measure, the normal way it's done.
Now what's the issue? Why should that be a problem again if
both sides agree to it? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says that the
problem is that if we normally do it flat and I'm going
to say Michael, I know we normally do it flat but I
want to give you a little extra I'm going to do a
heap, what should be the problem? It's between the two of us.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says well the problem is that other people
will see and that could
lead it that other buyers feel compelled to do it when that's
really not the practice or something of that nature. And certainly you
understand the reverse. If normally we heap and Michael says you know
what Dove it's okay, I know you're having a hard time, just
do a flat measure, you don't have to do a heaping measure,
and I just do the flat measure, then other buyers will feel
entitled, oh look, Dove sold with a flat measure, we're going to
sell, so it's going to sort of disrupt the norms of the
place and not give people what normally they would be entitled to,
it'll either hurt the buyer or hurt the seller. Okay that's the
way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it. תוספות Tosafos says a slightly different
explanation. One minute, let's keep on reading a little bit more. ומנין
שאם אמר הריני מוחק במקום שגודשין ולפחות לו מן הדמים Uminayin she'im
amar hareni mokech bemakom shegodshin ulephachot lo min hadamim Okay fine.
I was just about to ask that.
Excellent, you see, that's why all good things come to those who
wait. So let's say you say, okay listen, we're going to do
it, but you know, but we're not going to change the norms
because we're going to actually I'll smooth it out but Michael will
pay less. והריני גודש במקום שמוחקין Vahareini godeish bimkom shemochkin or I'll
give him I'll do an amount ולהוסיף לו על הדמים Ulehosif lo
al hadamim and he'll pay more. So we're not really changing how
much you get for how much money you pay. How do you
know you're not supposed to do that?
ומנין שאין שומעין לו? Uminayin she’ein shomin lo? How do you know
you don't listen? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אבן שלמה וצדק יהיה לך.
Even sheleimah vatzedek yiheyeh lach. It should be. The extra word tells
you not to do this. Now what's the big deal about this?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says the same basic point, that nobody knows,
people just see the visuals, nobody knows whether Michael's paid more or
less than the norm. So nevertheless it still disrupts the norms of
the place when you do a different thing even if somehow you
have paid for it or you know made up the difference in
money. Yes.
The ראש, Rosh, I thought the רשב"ם Rashbam slightly the nuance is
not that it disrupts the norms, but רמאות, rama'ut, like people will
come to be active cheaters. They'll say I saw him do that.
Doesn't he make that point that it's like a matter of רמאות?
rama'ut?
Yeah, I mean,
it's a little different than...
Right, that's true. I mean, but the key is דאיכא דחזי במדידה
ולא ידע לא בפחת ולא בתוספת. De’ika dechazi bimdidah velo yada lo
bifchas velo betosefes. Right,
people see visually what happened and they don't know that the difference
of the money. So you're right, what does that lead to? I
mean how exactly it leads to deceptive practices. I mean the deceptive
practices would be the next door keeper would say, look Dove did
it smooth, I'm going to do it smooth. Right, okay, that's what
I meant included in yeah yeah yeah.
But in these cases this is specifically a problem of מדות, middos,
but in terms of קנינים, kinyanim, if we decide we're going to
come up with an alternate קנין kinyan that the people agree on.
Yeah, that's a different thing, yeah. We've discussed that. Yeah, but no
that's not... You can't create a private קנין. kinyan. We've discussed we've
been discussing the other day a certain type of קנין kinyan that's
accepted amongst people of a certain profession, you know of a certain
trade. That's a different story. You can't come up with a private
קנין. kinyan. Okay, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, okay so now it says
like this. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, yeah?
This note says the difference between a heap and a level is
two-thirds, two as much of a level measure contains two-thirds as much.
Yeah, the heap is a third more. That's a huge... Yeah, I
don't know what to do with those statements like the same way
in the משנה mishna where it says that you tip it a
whole טפח, tefach, right? It seems like a huge difference. I mean
if there's really that much of a difference, then you're going to
have to adjust your prices for it. You know what I mean?
So it's not going to... It's like it's going to be... You're
not going to... Only if you maintain a small difference will it
not affect the pricing. If you're going to have a big difference,
if I'm going to have to add thirty-three percent, then I'm going
to tell you something, I'm going to be charging a lot more,
you know, and adjusting the price. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מנין
שאין מעיינין במקום שמכריעין ואין מכריעין במקום
שמעיינין. Minayin she’ein me’aynin bimkom shemachri’in ve’ein machri’in bimkom sheme’aynin. How do
you know? Now מעיינין me’aynin means like you investigate, but also עין,
ayin, the word עין ayin means eye level. How do you know
that you do not, you know, do things at exact eye level
at a balance in the place where when they do the balancing
they tip the scale? Okay, מכריע machri’ah means to decide, but you
understand that the word מכריע machri’ah to decide is because if you're
weighing between two options and you decide in favor of one, you
are tipping the scales in that person... in the favor of that
opinion. So מכריעין machri’in means to tip the scales and create an
imbalance in the scales. What? Right, exactly. So it's interesting to sort
of see how those metaphors play out. So מנין שאין מעיינין במקום
שמכריעין? Minayin she’ein me’aynin bimkom shemachri’in? How do you know you don't
sell it at eye level in a place where the way is
to tip the scales? ואין מכריעין במקום שמעיינין, Ve’ein machri’in bimkom sheme’aynin,
and you don't do the reverse, you don't tip it where it's
to do it at eye level. Get it? Even if you do
it at eye level, you would throw in an extra apple or
something. That's our משנה. mishna. But nevertheless, again, this is the question
about the norms of how do you do the initial measuring. תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, אבן שלמה. Even sheleimah. So the same way איפה
eifah is a volume measure, אבן even is a weight measure. Same
idea. ומנין שאם אמר הריני מעיין במקום שמכריעין ולפחות לו מן הדמים.
Uminayin she’im amar hareni me’ayein bimkom shemachri’in velifchos lo min hadamim. No
no no, I'm going to do it at eye level but I'll
give him a discount. והריני מכריע במקום שמעיינין ולהוסיף לו מן הדמים
Vahareini machri’ah bimkom sheme’aynin ulehosif lo min hadamim or I'm going to
tip it but I'll charge him more. שאין שומעין לו. She’ein shomin
lo. How do you know you don't listen? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
אבן שלמה וצדק. Even sheleimah vatzedek. So וצדק vatzedek means like it
always has to be that way, it's consistent.
It's literally describing like when you bake a cake and you have
a measuring cup. So you put it eye level to see that
it's the right... Exactly. So there's another way to measure? Like I
measure at eye level to be accurate.
Yeah, that's our משנה. mishna. The way in which you make sure
that the buyer is not getting cheated is you make sure that
it tips to a certain degree. Remember the משנה? mishna? A טפח?
tefach? I mean, I don't understand a טפח, tefach, that's huge. But
it says the way you measure is that what's consistent... When you're
buying a pound, what buying a pound means is I put a
pound on this side and this side has to go a טפח
tefach down. You know, a טפח tefach below the level. What? Right,
exactly.
The baker's dozen?
The baker's dozen, right. Right. But there's again, there's difference, right? If
it's מעיינין, me’aynin, it's you do the exact amount and you throw
in an extra unit, that's like the baker's dozen. And מכריעין machri’in
is that the actual measuring is if you buy a pound, I'm
going to put a pound and... you know. and five ounces on
the scale. Thank you so much, everyone. Thank you, Eli, yeah.
So that טפח tefach is going to depend on the particular scale,
how large it is.
Right. We're going to get to that at the end of the
דף. daf. Okay, let's keep on going. Okay, so thank you, Eli,
I appreciate it. All right, so it says, okay, תנו
רבנן ושפטתם צדק.
Tanu Rabbanan
v'shafat-tem tzedek. אמר רב יהודה משורא: Amar Rav Yehuda Mi-Sura: לא יהיה
לך בביתך אבן ואבן. Lo yihyeh lecha b'veitecha even va-aven. So this
is going to be a very cute read, I shouldn't say cute,
a very powerful midrashic read of the פסוק. pasuk. So לא יהיה
לך בביתך, lo yihyeh lecha b'veitecha, you won't have anything in your
house. You'll be dirt poor. Okay, מה טעם? ma ta'am? Why would
somebody be poor and have nothing in their house?
משום איפה ואיפה, Mishum eifah v'eifah, because the person has two different
measures in their house. So לא יהיה לך בביתך איפה ואיפה, lo
yihyeh lecha b'veitecha eifah v'eifah, you shouldn't have two measures, meaning I
have two, you know, it's like two sets of books. The books
you show the IRS, the books you keep internally. I got two
measures. I got the measure I buy with and the measure I
sell with, right? And the measure I buy with is bigger and
the measure I sell with is smaller, right? Or if it's a
weight measure, right, the measure I buy with is, same way, the
measure I buy with is heavier and the measure I sell with
is lighter. All right. So if you are holding those two types
of disparate measures in order to deceive people, so that's לא יהיה
לך בביתך. lo yihyeh lecha b'veitecha. Then you'll become poor. מה טעם
לא יהיה לך בביתך? מה טעם? משום איפה ואיפה, Ma ta'am lo
yihyeh lecha b'veitecha? Ma ta'am? Mishum eifah v'eifah, because you're holding on
to these two sets of measures. לא יהיה לך בכיסך. Lo yihyeh
lecha b'chisecha. You won't have anything in your pocket. מה טעם? משום
אבן ואבן, Ma ta'am? Mishum even va-aven, because you have two sets
of weight measures. אבל אבן שלמה וצדק יהיה לך. Aval even shleimah
va-tzedek yihyeh lach. If you have a just, you know, a just
weight, then יהיה לך, yihyeh lach, then you'll have wealth, you'll become
wealthy. איפה שלמה וצדק יהיה לך, Eifah shleimah va-tzedek yihyeh lach, and
if you have a just measure, then יהיה לך, yihyeh lach, you
will have much money. Okay, very nice read, a very nice midrashic
read of the פסוק. pasuk. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: יהיה לך. yihyeh
lach. Okay, now again, ignoring the לא. lo. Okay, anyway, no, but
the question is which part of the פסוק pasuk are you reading,
right? It's אבן שלמה וצדק יהיה לך. Even shleimah va-tzedek yihyeh lach.
So it's reading the יהיה לך yihyeh lach as not just a
personal thing of my personal measures, but reading it at the communal
level, which is interesting, by the way, because often the מדרש הלכה
midrash halacha is sensitive to the fact that the use of the
singular, of the singular pronoun,
often means that we're not talking to the individuals but we're talking
to the whole community as a collective. It's a little bit opposite
of what you would have thought, but if you think about it,
it makes sense. When it's לכם, lachem, it means all of you,
you as a plurality, you as multiple people. If it's לך, lecha,
it could be talking to an individual, but it could be talking
to the community as a whole. Actually, this is very relevant for
ספירת העומר, Sefirat HaOmer, allow me for a moment to digress, because
there's a מצוה mitzvah of ספירת העומר, Sefirat HaOmer, וספרתם לכם ממחרת
השבת, u-sefartem lachem mimacharat ha-shabbat, but by יובל, Yovel, right, it
says וספרת לך שבע שבתות שנים. v'safarta lecha sheva shabbatot shanim. And
the מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says מניין, minayin, how do you know
that every individual is not obligated to count ספירת היובל? Sefirat HaYovel?
Why don't we have to count ספירת היובל, Sefirat HaYovel, count the
years? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: וספרת לך. v'safarta lecha. So what does
it mean? So לך lecha means that it's a communal obligation. As
a nation we count, which means the בית דין Beit Din does
the counting for the יובל, Yovel, but וספרתם לכם u-sefartem lachem means
every individual is obligated to count. I might say the opposite, מניין
שכל אחד ואחד חייב לספור? תלמוד לומר: וספרתם לכם. Minayin she-kol echad
v'echad chayav lispor? Talmud lomar: u-sefartem lachem. So the גמרא Gemara does
the same here. It says איפה שלמה וצדק יהיה לך. Eifah shleimah
va-tzedek yihyeh lach. You as, what?
Doesn't work with the הגדה: Haggadah: מה העבודה הזאת לכם? Mah ha-avodah
ha-zot lachem? לכם, Lachem, ולא לו.
v'lo lo.
That's true, that's true. But it means he's also not part of
the individuals either, but it's a good point. Anyway, so this means
you as a community have to ensure that you have just weights
and measures, not just every individual. Okay, so this is a very
nice דרשה. drasha. So יהיה לך: yihyeh lach: מלמד שמעמידים אגדרמין למידות.
melamed she-ma'amidim agardemin l'middot. So אגדרמין agardemin is some type of a,
you know, community official to go ahead and to make sure that
everybody, you know, to test and make sure that everybody's measures are
correct. Charlie will probably tell us what the Greek word means, okay,
after this you'll tell us when you find out. ואין מעמידים אגדרמין
לשערים. V'ein ma'amidim agardemin l'sha'arim. But you do not create city officials
to make sure that there is no collusion, no setting of prices.
Now why not? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says because you don't have
to go ahead and check that a person's individual prices are higher
than the normal, good, you know, just regular competition, right, free market
economy will ensure that the prices reach very, you know, come to
their appropriate level. Because if you have inflated prices, I'll undersell you
and I'll make money. Of course, what that ignores is the possibility
of collusion. Okay, but it's very interesting that you basically are saying
the free market economy will take care of prices reaching their natural
level, but cheating with weights and measures, you need there to be
city officials. Yes, Charlie.
אגדרמין, Agadormin, אגדרמין agardomin is from a Greek word that means the
officer in charge of the market or inspector for what is being
sold in the market.
Excellent. Exactly what it means in this context. Okay, so I don't
know if I should say this, but I still remember from my
youth when I was a teenager that the government, the city government
or the state government, I don't know, sent officials incognito to various
butcher stores to buy meat and they would buy a pound of
meat and then they would step outside the store and then they'd
weigh it. And they would see whether they actually got a full
pound,
and the store, one of the stores that was found to be
cheating was the kosher butcher. So there you go, right? So it's
exactly whatever, that you need city officials to be checking up. And
by the way, another version which is also relevant to laws of
כשרות, kashrut, is for many years I was getting questions about like
can you buy in an non-kosher store a fish, like let's say
a white-fleshed fish that doesn't have fins and scales, if they label
it and they tell you what it is. Well these are- and
all along I was saying like I don't know because if you
can't identify it by sight, like you can by salmon and tuna,
like
it's a general question in הלכה. halacha. How much do we think
that a fear of somebody cheating and being found out will make
sure that they're being honest in business? And how much do you
think that that's enough of a concern- enough of a concern. So
I would always tell people I don't think you can trust that.
Anyway, starting like about ten fifteen years ago they started finding out
and I think what I remember hearing was it started with two
girls that did this as a high school science fair project. They
went to stores and they bought fish and then they did DNA
testing on the fish. Anyway, it is extremely pervasive that like thirty
percent of fish are mislabeled. So intentionally because it's for the cheaper
ones as the more expensive ones. So anyway, so you really need
city officials to make sure people do this, yes. Yeah.
And the prices. Until the nineteens- for decades, until the 1970s there
were in the United States something called fair trade laws that prohibited
underselling what the manufacturer suggested price.
Interesting. Okay. So that's interesting. Alright. So anyway, so that's the principle.
So you have to have city officials to make sure that the
sales are- that the weight and measures are correct, but not for
the actual market prices. דבי נשיא אוקמי אגרדמי בין למידות בין לשערים.
Debe Nesia ukmi agordemi bein le-middot bein le-shearim. Now the house of
the נשיא Nasi put
in בבל Bavel here, not in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, put up
what do you call it, officials for- I think it's- שמואל Shmuel
is בבל, Bavel, right? Yes, שמואל's Shmuel בבל. Bavel. Yeah. So anyway
put up officials in- both for the weights and for the prices.
אמר ליה שמואל לקרנא Amar lei Shmuel le-Karna so שמואל Shmuel says
to קרנא, Karna, his student/colleague, פוק תני להו מעמידין אגרדמי למידות ואין
מעמידין אגרדמי לשערים. Puk tani le-hu ma'amidin agordemi le-middot ve-ein ma'amidin agordemi
le-shearim. Go teach the house of the נשיא Nasi the הלכה halacha
that מעמידין אגרדמי למידות ואין מעמידין אגרדמי לשערים. ma'amidin agordemi le-middot ve-ein
ma'amidin agordemi le-shearim. No, you only do it for measures, not for
the actual setting of prices. Now that's a little funny because it's
like I understand saying you don't have an obligation to do it
for setting the prices, but what's the problem with it? I guess
the problem would be that maybe you're improperly deflating prices. It's not
fair to the sellers, right? If you're setting up and you've decided
arbitrarily,
oh milk cannot be for more than a dollar and a quarter
a pound and I'm going to see anything higher as an overcharging,
that's not necessarily fair to the sellers. Okay. So anyway so he
said go teach them this. Now very nice to give קרנא Karna
that job to go teach the בי נשיא Be Nesia that they're
doing the wrong thing. So פוק תני להו, puk tani le-hu, so
קרנא Karna went down and he taught to them- מעמידין אגרדמי- ma'amidin
agordemi
I'm sorry, no that's what he said. נפק דרש להו מעמידין אגרדמי
בין למידות בין לשערים. Nafak darash le-hu ma'amidin agordemi bein le-middot bein
le-shearim. He went out
and he explicated, you put officials for both. So אמר ליה, amar
lei, so שמואל Shmuel said to him מה שמך? ma shimcha? What's
your name? קרנא? Karna? Horn? קרנא? Karna? תיפוק ליה קרנא בין עיני.
Tepuk lei karna bein einai. So a horn should come out between
your eyes. So you see that's the source of the idea that
Jews have horns. So anyway, נפקא ליה קרנא בין עיני nafka lei
karna bein einai and so it happened that a horn came out.
By the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam gives another story in the גמרא
שבת Gemara Shabbat where שמואל Shmuel got upset for קרנא Karna for
a different reason and according to that story that's why the horn
came out between his eyes. So anyway, so he said well maybe
both happened and then we attributed it to both. Anyway, ואי הוא
כמאן סבר? Ve-ihu kaman savar? Now who did קרנא Karna hold like?
Because we're going to assume that even if he might be a
little bit intimidated by the בי נשיא Be Nesia he wouldn't tell
them something that would not be according to an acceptable halachic opinion.
כי הא דאמר רמי בר חמא אמר רב יצחק מעמידין אגרדמי בין
למידות בין לשערים מפני הרמאים. Ki ha de-amar Rami bar Chama amar
Rav Yitzchak ma'amidin agordemi bein le-middot bein le-shearim mipnei ha-ramaim. No,
there is a teaching that you do it even for- not just
for the weight and measures, but even for the prices, because of
those that are- because of the deceivers. Now what can the deceivers
do? So the most obvious explanation I would say is that they
could just have collusion for prices, which we know happens all along.
Okay, the רשב"ם Rashbam says מפני שמוכרין ביוקר ואומרים שהוסיפו במידה שנתן
להם המכס מלמעלה. mipnei she-mochrin be-yoker ve-omrim she-hosifu be-middah she-natan la-hem ha-meches
mi-le-ma'alah.
So he actually tries to say that it's not just for what
price they're setting. Meaning it's for more general- Quality. Exactly. It's for
more general, checking up. what you're doing, meaning so it's not just
checking your weights and measures, it's like are you selling grade A
and calling—are you selling grade B and calling it grade A, or
other types of tricks. So that's not exactly the point because the
משנה Mishnah says—right, exactly, the משנה Mishnah says מפני השערים. mipnei hasharim.
So I think more logically it's because of collusion. And by the
way, you should be aware that this happened a lot particularly by
people taking advantage when there was religious requirements for Jews to buy
things. So for example, I mean we just came through פסח, Pesach,
you know, the way the—right, and the way the prices are so
inflated for פסח. Pesach. I've often thought that the כשרות Kashrus industries
should say we're not going to give you a הכשר לפסח hechsher
le-Pesach unless you adjust your prices accordingly. But historically this happened a
lot, for example, ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, people would sell—because it was
such a הקפדה hakfada to have fish for שבת, Shabbos, that the
fishmongers would actually inflate their prices for fish. And what happened is
it led to communities, the Rabbis in communities basically saying it's אסור
assur to buy fish for שבת Shabbos until—until the prices go down.
So they would actually use, you know, their communal control in order
to control, you know, to do that. I mean, you actually have
that in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara speaks of—there's some cases
like that in the גמרא Gemara where people raised their prices because
the community needs it for religious reasons, and then the Rabbis say
we're going to forbid everybody to buy it until you do something
about it. So anyway,
what?
Something about funerals and whether you can—like,
well the גמרא, Gemara, right, said that people used to spend a
lot of money on funerals, and that happens now, that people feel
very guilty, you know, somebody died or whatever and the funeral parlors
like make them spend a lot more money, so that's why we
adopted a principle. But that was like not just a temporary, you
know, reaction, that was an ongoing we're only going to do the
bare minimum type of thing.
Right, right, there's that—I forget who it is who did—someone asked him
like if the Jewish funeral home is totally price gouging, then
can—is it like פטור patur to go to a, like,
a non-Jewish—right, right, interesting, and
I think—I don't know what the תשובה teshuvah was, I forget.
Right, right, yeah, so it's very interesting the way community, you know,
Rabbis and community leaders, you know, had to take responsibility for this.
Okay, wait, we're going to go on. Okay, so what? What?
They also do that with
the Gentiles, right, right, for a very different reason, not to encourage
further behavior, right. Okay, we're moving on. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
like this. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. היה מבקש ממנו ליטרא שוקל לו
ליטרא. hayah mevakesh mimenu litra shokel lo litra.
You mentioned about whether or not we
do—whether or not you can—yeah, but it looks like the פסק הלכה
psak Halacha here was that you do, which is interesting.
רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens like רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak.
Yeah, well that's sort of where the letter is, which is pretty
funny since the horn went out between the eyes. Okay. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. היה מבקש ממנו ליטרא שוקל לו ליטרא. hayah mevakesh mimenu
litra shokel lo litra. If somebody buys a pound, use a pound
weight to counter-balance. חצי ליטרא שוקל לו חצי ליטרא. chatzi litra shokel
lo chatzi litra. רביע ליטרא שוקל לו רביע ליטרא. revia litra shokel
lo revia litra. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קמשמע לן? mai
kamashmalan?
What's he coming to hear?
So—right, דמתקנינן מתקילי עד הכא, dematkinen matkilei ad hacha, that you have
to have all these different measures because if you basically have, I
don't know, like, I don't know, like just big measures, maybe you're
going to—you're going to estimate or you force people to overbuy. Another
reason also is that—a concern the גמרא's Gemara going to have later
is if you have measures that are too close to each other,
like a quarter, a third, and a fifth, and three-eighths, then you'll
be able to swap them because it's very—the differences are too small.
So here it's telling you no, no, what you can do is
you can have full, half, quarter, eighth, those differences are large enough
that you don't have to worry, those are the measures you should
have. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. היה מבקש ממנו שלושה רביעי ליטרא.
hayah mevakesh mimenu shlosha reviei litra. You wanted to buy three quarters
of a pound. This is like a good little riddle, what would
you do? So I would say you would put the half and
the quarter pound on one side and the meat on the other
side. So the גמרא Gemara says לא יאמר לו שוקל לי שלושה
רביעי ליטרא אחת אחת. lo yomar lo shokel li shlosha reviei litra
achat achat. So the גמרא Gemara says maybe you should do—make three
one-quarter measures. It's always a good question when you're cooking at home
and it tests for three quarters, you know, three—what is it, like
three halves of a—three quarters of a tablespoon. Do you take your
one-quarter tablespoon and do it three times, or your one-half tablespoon? But
that's an effort question. Anyway, so it says do not do, do
not measure out three quarter
pounds. אלא, ela, what do you do? לא יאמר לו שוקל לי
אלא שוקל ליטרא ומניח רביע ליטרא עם הבשר. lo yomar lo shokel
li ela shokel litra umeiniach revia litra im habasar. You put a
one pound weight on this side of the scale and you put
a quarter pound weight plus the meat on this side of the
scale and then they balance, which is interesting. I don't understand why
you don't weigh three times, the רשב"ם Rashbam says because every time
you're weighing, even if it's a place where they do eye-level weighing,
right, even if they do eye-level, you know, and you're waiting for
the thing to go to the middle, you're always going to a
little bit if you're honest, you know, make sure that it's a
little bit more, you know, in favor of the buyer because you
can't be totally precise, right? So—so if you do it three times,
the buyer wins out three times. Okay, so I get why you
don't do three separate weighings, but what I don't get is why
you don't do a half and a quarter on this side and
a, you know, and a, you know, and the meat on the
other side. That I don't
understand.
But anyway. Alright. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. היה מבקש ממנו עשר ליטרין.
hayah mevakesh mimenu eser litrin. You wanted—somebody wants to buy ten pounds.
לא יאמר לו שקול לי אחת אחת והכריע. Lo yomar lo shkol
li achat achat v'yachria. So just weigh out for me
ten separate one-pound weighings, and with each weighing you get a tip
in his favor. אלא שוקלן כולן בבת אחת. Ela shoklan kulan b'vat
achat. You put all ten pounds of meat on one side, then
you have to have a lot of single pound weights, or you
have larger weights, you have five-pound weights and ten-pound weights.
ונותן הכרע אחד לכולן, V'noten hechra echad l'kulan, and he only gets
one tipping in his favor. תנו רבנן. Tanna Rabbanan.
נפש מאזנים תלויה באוויר. Nefesh moznayim tluya ba'avir. Now the נפש מאזנים
nefesh moznayim is the actual, the whole scale is called the נפש
מאזנים. nefesh moznayim. I don't know why it's called נפש, nefesh, but
anyway, that's like the whole scale, the whole balance, okay? So it's
תלויה באוויר ג' טפחים tluya ba'avir gimmel tefachim וגבוה מן הארץ ג'
טפחים. v'gvoha min ha'aretz gimmel tefachim. So you would have if you
would have a large one, you would actually suspend it from the
ceiling, okay? If here's my ceiling and here's my thing, and here
it is suspended from the ceiling.
Okay,
so it's suspended from the ceiling. So depending on how heavy the
things are you're going to weigh, and the גמרא Gemara is going
to discuss it and the ברייתא Beraita is going to discuss it.
Are you weighing gold? Are you weighing meat? Are you weighing iron?
So you have to allow, but so if it's mostly small things
you're going to weigh, even when it's imbalanced, you put it on
one side before you put the other side, it's not going to
go up too much, but if it's very heavy things, the imbalance
can be very large. So you have to have enough space at
the top so that when it tips in a certain way, this
thing doesn't get blocked by the top. Now I don't know why
that should matter because that's just a practical thing. Let it get
blocked by the top or whatever, but I don't know, maybe it'll
throw it off. Similarly, if it's not suspended from the ceiling, if
it's suspended on some other type of a thing and it's near
the ground, it has to be a certain distance off the ground
for the same reason, that it doesn't tip out of proportion. Okay,
so נפש מאזנים תלויה באוויר ג' טפחים. Nefesh moznayim tluya ba'avir gimmel
tefachim.
It's three טפחים tefachim removed, minimum three טפחים tefachim removed from the
ceiling, וגבוה מן הארץ ג' טפחים, v'gvoha min ha'aretz gimmel tefachim, minimum
three טפחים tefachim off of the ground. והקנה והמחתה שלה י"ב טפחים.
V'hakaneh v'hamachta shela yod-bet tefachim.
This is called the קנה, kaneh, the stick here that goes in
the middle, and the מחתה masna are the ropes. So those are
twelve טפחים. tefachim. It's a funny way to measure it, but basically
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, it means that the stick
here is four טפחים, tefachim, which is like a foot long, and
the ropes here
are also, it's like a divide by three. The ropes are as
long as the bar.
So I mean, if this gets half of it, so it's anyway.
And what's the נפש nefesh in this side?
The נפש nefesh is like the whole thing.
והוא ברזל חלול שהלשון קבוע בו. V'hu barzel chalul shehalashon kavua bo.
שהלשון Shehalashon what, this?
But that's the קנה. kaneh.
I don't know, the רשב"ם Rashbam says הוא ברזל... hu barzel...
He says it on the word נפש? nefesh?
Yeah, נפש של מאזנים הוא ברזל חלול שהלשון קבוע בו. Nefesh shel
moznayim hu barzel chalul shehalashon kavua bo. Oh,
I thought that was like the needle maybe that goes, is there
a needle that goes up there's a needle that goes up? That's
a different kind.
That's not the bar across. No.
Yeah, that sounds like it's this, but this is the קנה. kaneh.
Oh, you don't think the קנה kaneh is the other stick?
No, he says the
קנה kaneh is הוא הקנה שהלשון קבוע באמצעיתו. hu hakaneh shehalashon kavua
b'emtzaito. He uses the exact same words for describing the קנה kaneh
as he does for the נפש. nefesh. He says הלשון קבוע באמצעיתו.
halashon kavua b'emtzaito. Oh, he says הלשון קבוע בו? halashon kavua bo?
I don't know. You can try to figure it out, I don't
know. But it's clear that he says קנה kaneh is this. So
if this plus the ropes are twelve טפחים, tefachim, it means this
is four טפחים tefachim and the length of the ropes is four
טפחים. tefachim. So that's on both sides, so that's twelve טפחים. tefachim.
So that's a foot long rope. That's a lot. That's a pretty
big, think about that, a foot long bar, a foot long rope
on each side, that's big.
I've seen in the illustration they don't, you're saying each string is
four? This
thing doesn't look like each string is four.
What, that the strings combined equal four?
I don't know, I'm just pointing
that they make the strings look shorter. I was wondering that because
it would seem funny to have such a long...
Yeah, that would be really big.
No, but I'm not so sure.
And this picture
is what like what you're saying?
That the length of the string is four. Yeah. And this is...
but you think about it, if this is two on each side,
so it doesn't look that as imbalanced. If that's two on each
side, and then this, oh no, it does look even more imbalanced
because that's two on each side.
Always has this much longer like this.
Yeah. That's how I understood the רשב"ם.
Rashbam. This Steinsaltz system is much like what you're doing. So anyway.
He doesn't have measurements, but it's...
I mean, I want you to point out that if you have
longer... I can't exactly remember my physics, but I do know intuitively
that if you have longer strings or whatever, it's much more sensitive
scale, any slight... imbalance, a slight imbalance will cause a much bigger
movement of the center. Some scientist here can confirm that or not.
Okay. Anyway. All right. So, okay. וקנה ומיתנא של שני טפחים. Vekaneh
u'masna shel shenei tefachim. ושל צמרים. Veshel tzemarim. Now
we haven't said what you're using to weight that weight for that,
we'll talk about it in a minute. But now we're going to
talk about the different sizes for ones that are weighing lighter objects.
Things are used by wool sellers ושל זגגין Veshel zigagin and glass
sellers. It's very interesting. They would sell glass by weight. תלויה באויר
שני טפחים. Tluyah ba'avir shenei tefachim. If that's for
you're going to be weighing lighter things, so it doesn't have to
be as much removed from the ceiling. Only two טפחים tefachim removed
from the ceiling. וגובה מן הארץ שני טפחים Vegovah min ha'aretz shenei
tefachim and a minimum of two טפחים tefachim off the ground. וקנה
ומיתנא שלו תשעה טפחים. Vekaneh u'masna shelo tish'ah tefachim. And the combined
bar with the rope is nine טפחים, tefachim, which means three טפחים
tefachim for the bar and three טפחים tefachim for each side of
the ropes.
What was the מאזניים moznayim that we just first?
The גמרא's Gemara going to ask. ושל חנוני ושל בעל הבית. Veshel
chanvani veshel ba'al habayis.
If it's a storekeeper or a homeowner, which you're selling presumably even
lighter things.
But I guess the what do you call it the wool seller
and the glass seller are more wholesalers. But if you're selling at
the retail level, you're selling smaller quantities. So תלויה באויר טפח וגובה
מן הארץ טפח. Tluyah ba'avir tefach vegovah min ha'aretz tefach. So it
only needs to be a minimum of a טפח. tefach. וקנה ומיתנא
שלו ששה טפחים. Vekaneh u'masna shelo shishah tefachim. Notice this last one
is always divisible by three because it's the bar plus the ropes
on each side. It's six, which means okay, which means two טפחים
tefachim of the bar and two טפחים tefachim of the ropes on
each side. ושל תורטני. Veshel turtani. And תורטני turtani here is somebody
that sells basically like precious metals. It means like a
smith, okay? תלויה באויר שלשה אצבעות. Tluyah ba'avir sheloshah etzba'os. So you're
selling much smaller quantities. So therefore it's only three fingers, half a
טפח. tefach. וגובה מן הארץ שלשה אצבעות. Vegovah min ha'aretz sheloshah etzba'os.
וקנה ומיתנא שלו איני יודע, Vekaneh u'masna shelo eini yodea, which is
fascinating. Like I don't know exactly what the right size is for
the bar and for the ropes. Which is so fascinating. Like why
if he knows all these other numbers, how does the author not
know the numbers here? But I also do wonder again because
because these are precious metals, on the one hand you're selling smaller
quantities, but on the other hand you want a much more precise
precise weighing, right? So you want a much more sensitive scale. So
I would think that you would want longer ropes. I mean again,
if somebody here correct me if they know the physics better. But
I think the longer the rope, then the more every little amount
of weight causes a bigger shift, right? So I would think you
would want longer ropes here. Anyway. ואלא הא קמייתא דמאי. Ve'ella ha
kamaisa demai. So anyway, so now that we've described all these different
sellers or things you're selling and their different sizes, the first one,
which we said it was you know 12 טפחים, tefachim, four and
four and four and three טפחים, tefachim, that was the one that
sold the biggest stuff. What are you selling there? So אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, דגורמי. degurmei. So דגורמי, degurmei, which is the
רש"י Rashi says it means smiths of like of brass and iron.
So they sell, you know, a lot of very weight heavy stuff
which is not so precious and therefore you need a scale that's
very big. Okay. אמר רב מני בר פטיש, Amar Rav Mani bar
Patish, כדרך שאמרו לענין איסורין כך אמרו לענין טומאתן. Kederech she'amru le'inyan
issurin kach amru le'inyan tumasan. Now
the what's the reason for giving these these what do you call
it, these dimensions? So it says for איסור. issur. What does איסור
issur mean? It's funny, איסור issur normally we think means ritual. But
here it means actually the איסורין issurin of cheating in business. And
the or the obligation to have just weights and measures. So part
of just weights and measures is that your scale, it's not only
the weights you put on your scale, right? It's whether you know
you could sort of rig your scale as well. Or even if
it's not rigging to create an imbalance, you could rig it so
that there's a slight imprecision in it. And the imprecision favors you,
you know? So it's not as sensitive as it should be. So
the same way we've given all of these numbers for the proper
sensitivity in whatever structure for the honesty in measures, the same is
true for טומאה. tumah. That is something considered a כלי kli for
טומאה tumah or not. So if it's not made properly, it's not
actually a כלי kli for טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי קא משמע לן? Mai ka mashma lan? What are you telling
me? תנינא, Tanina, we taught that in a משנה. Mishnah. חוט מאזנים
של חנוני ושל בעלי בתים טפח. Chut moznayim shel chanvani veshel ba'alei
batim tefach. That the that the string here of is
this that's what's called the חוט מאזנים chut moznayim is a טפח.
tefach. And that's exactly that's a משנה Mishnah in כלים. Keilim. And
that's exactly what we just taught, which is is that it has
to be a טפח tefach removed from the ceiling. So it's already
we've already taught that in כלים. Keilim. So the גמרא Gemara says
no,
קנה ומיתנא שלו איצטריכא ליה לא תנן. Kaneh u'masna shelo itztericha leh
lo tenan. No, that משנה Mishnah in כלים Keilim tells you this,
but it doesn't tell you the dimensions of the bar and of
the ropes. So therefore that's why we had to teach our ברייתא
Baraisa to tell you those dimensions. And that those dimensions, the same
way those are necessary for laws of honest weight and measures, those
are also necessary for defining a כלי kli for טומאה tumah purposes.
Now I should say that תוספות Tosafos says for those that are
interested in טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, that this would be a כלי.
kli. Even if the even if the measures were off. Meaning like,
you know, it's an interesting question, right? Let's say, I don't know,
here's an example, let's say I made a spoon and it was
supposed to be- it was supposed to be a measure for a
tablespoon and actually it was only eight tenths of a tablespoon. Would
I say oh, it's not מקבל טומאה mekabel Tuma because it's not
doing what it's supposed to be doing? What do you mean? It's
a metal vessel that has a בית קיבול beis kibul that's functional.
What do you mean it's not מקבל טומאה? mekabel Tuma? So תוספות
Tosfos says if this is off, it's still מקבל טומאה, mekabel Tuma,
but the relevance is for הלכה halacha about a יד לטומאה. yad
letuma. יד לטומאה Yad letuma means that something that's attached to a
vessel, if I go ahead and I touch something טמא tamei to
the string, is that מטמא metamei the actual container? Right, or the
bar. Is that מטמא metamei the container? Is that seen as an
extension and a conveyor of טומאה? Tuma? So there he says it
has to be considered something that is an appropriate handle for it,
an appropriate, you know, sort of attachment to it. Something that's not
an appropriate attachment would not be a conveyor of טומאה. Tuma. So
תוספות Tosfos reads it in a slightly different way.
Yeah? Can you say one word about like- it has to be
a בית קיבול, beis kibul, right? Like it's in במה מדליקין Bameh
Madlikin that if you make a wick, you know, whether it's מקבל
טומאה mekabel Tuma or not? Yeah.
But- well no, only in- I mean wood has to be a
בית קיבול. beis kibul. Metal doesn't- I should- I said it before
but metal and בית קיבול, beis kibul, metal doesn't even need a
בית קיבול. beis kibul. Only wood needs a בית קיבול. beis kibul.
But what about things like a wick?
That's like a בגד, beged, that's like a different story, different, yeah,
yeah, yeah. Alright, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין עושין, Ein osin, okay,
אין עושין משקלות לא של בעץ ולא של אבר. ein osin mishkalos
lo shel ba'atz v'lo shel avar. You do not make the weights,
the actual weights themselves, out of בעץ. ba'atz. Now what's בעץ? ba'atz?
I'll tell you what תוספות Tosfos said בעץ ba'atz was. He said
tin.
I think some disagree.
Tin? I didn't even know the גמרא Gemara knew of tin. I
thought that was a more recent alloy.
It was- it was imported from as far away as Britain.
Wow. When? In Roman times? Wow. Okay.
Tin is an alloy? Yeah. No, it's- it's a metal.
It's a metal? Oh, what's the alloy?
Tin is alloyed with copper to make
aluminum- to make aluminum...
copper to make bronze.
To make bronze. Ah, right, right. Tin and copper together- oh, that's
the Bronze Age when they figured out how to alloy them.
They discovered the Bronze Age.
There you go. Okay, fine. Alright, אין עושין משקלות לא של... Ein
osin mishkalos lo shel...
It hardens metal.
Right, right. They had better weapons. אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu was Bronze
Age.
Okay, okay. אין עושין משקלות לא של בעץ, Ein osin mishkalos lo
shel ba'atz, you don't make out of tin. So what's that alloy
that we use a lot today? That's an alloy? Is it aluminum-
aluminum is an alloy? No, aluminum's- aluminum's a metal too.
Or brass is an alloy.
Okay, alright, fine. אין עושין משקלות לא של בעץ ולא של אבר,
Ein osin mishkalos lo shel ba'atz v'lo shel avar, you don't make
it out of tin or out of lead, ולא של גיסטרון, v'lo
shel gisteron, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says is just like a mixed
alloy of different metals, ולא של שאר מיני מתכות v'lo shel shear
minei matachos and not other metals, אלא עושה הוא של צונמא ושל
זכוכית, ela oseh hu shel tsunma v'shel zechuchis, but you can use
rock measures or glass measures. Now what is the problem with- with
these measures? With metal measures? I mean, are they afraid that they're
going to wear away? I mean, these are hard metals. So if
you take a look at
תוספות, Tosfos, אמר רבינו תם דוקא משקלות ששוקלים בשר ושומן שלכלוכית מדבק
בהן ומתייבש, Amar Rabbeinu Tam davka mishkalos sheshoklim basar v'shuman shelachluchis midabek
bahen u'misyabesh, okay,
ולא מטעם שחיקה כדפירש קונטרס. v'lo mita'am shechika k'difirash Kuntres. It's not
that the things will wear away. They won't wear away. I mean,
they're good strong metals. Okay? But the problem is that somehow- so
I don't understand- so he- I'm sorry, because it's not the weights,
excuse me. The משקלות mishkalos are not the weights. The משקלות mishkalos
are the pans. That was my mistake. The משקלות mishkalos are the
pans. Okay? So why shouldn't you be able to make a pan
here out of a metal? That would seem very reasonable. It won't
stick to things, it won't wear away. So he says no, the
reason is is because you're going to put meat on one- if
you put moist things on one side of the pan, okay, then
he says שלכלוכית מדבק בהן ומתייבש. shelachluchis midabek bahen u'misyabesh. I guess
what he means is that- that you'll get some residue. And if
you get some residue, remember it's like cleaning out the containers you
have to do? So even if you're doing a weighing, you have
to be afraid of residue. So he says if you make this
metal and you put meat on it and moist stuff on it,
there'll be a residue that'll be hard to get out. So that's
the issue. Okay? And then he goes on to discuss other issues
about like- and then he says, I'll just read one more line,
אבל משקלות ששוקלים בהן כסף וזהב, aval mishkalos sheshoklim bahen kesef v'zahav,
if you're using it for gold or silver, מותר לעשותן של מתכת,
mutar la'asosan shel mataches, you have to make the metal- you're allowed
to, because we're not afraid of residue, אלא שצריך לחפותו עור, ela
shetzarich lachaposo or, you have to line these with leather. Why do
you have to line it with leather? Because if you put gold
in your thing, you don't want to scrape off a little bit
of gold in the process, right? So therefore, in this case, you're
allowed to make the pan of metal, but you have to line
the pan with leather. You know, it's like when they showed you
something in this nice plush little velvet thing. Right, same idea. Okay,
so let's anyway- so that's it. You cannot make the- but that's
how תוספות Tosfos explains. So you don't actually make the pans out
of metal if you're going to use them for stuff that will
leave a residue. Yes, Charlie. Alloys...
Alloys, alloys would make it really easy to achieve a cheat if
you use them as the actual weights because a slight difference in
the alloy composition.
Aha, right, but we're not talking about the weights, that was my
mistake. We're talking about the pans. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, אין
עושים המחק. ein osim hamachak.
Now how about the thing you use to clean out the container?
You have a, you know, a one liter container and now you
want that's a, you know, your official measure and now you need
to clean it out from the residue. Now I don't exactly understand
the mechanics here, I gotta tell you, okay? But anyway, you don't
make it של דלעת, shel dala'at, you don't make it out of
a gourd, I know you stick in a gourd and you rub
it around the sides, I'm not exactly getting it. Maybe the footnote
explains it, I couldn't understand it, מפני שהוא קל, mipnei shehu kal,
cause that's too light and presumably won't do a good enough job
cleaning it out. ולא שף, velo shaf, ולא שף, velo shaf,
you can't scour with it.
Yeah, if it's too light. I mean it's soft, it won't whatever.
ולא של, veloshel, ולא של, veloshel, wait, ולא של מתכת veloshel matechet
מפני שהוא מכביד. mipnei shehu machbid. But you know, don't use go
ahead like I mean like what do they call it, the stuff
you use on those pads? A Brillo pad? A Brillo pad or
something like that, cause that might actually scrape away... I mean this
is the way I'm going to read it, I don't know if
that's how they explain it, cause that could scrape away at the
container and that'll cheat the seller, cause now his container will be,
you know, thinner, you know, will contain more volume than it should
because you're scraping away at the walls. That's how I'm reading it
anyway.
אלא, ela, אבל עושהו של זית ושל אגוז ושל שקמה ושל אשברוע.
aval osehu shel zayit veshel egoz veshel shikma veshel ashbro'a. You can
make it out of olive wood or nut wood or sycamore and
I don't know what אשברוע ashbro'a is. What?
They say boxwood.
Boxwood. Anyway, those are things that will clean it out well, that
will clean it out well without cutting, without scraping into it. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, fine. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, אין עושים את המחק
ein osim et hamachak צדו אחד עב וצדו אחד קצר. tziddo echad
av vetziddo echad katzar. You do not make it one side wide
and one side narrow because apparently if you do it the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, you know, if it's narrower, you can
get into the nooks and cranny and you can do a better
job. If it's wider, you know, if you think about trying to
stick a wide thing in to try to move it around, you're
not going to do as good of a job. So what does
it mean one side narrow and one side wide? It says well,
if I'm the buyer, I'll say wait, I want to clean out
the vessel and I'll clean it out with the narrow end to
make sure that I get the full size, and if I'm the
seller I'll say don't worry, I'll clean it out first and I'd
clean it out with the wide end. Okay, so don't sort of
like איפה ואיפה. eifah ve'eifah. You have to have a consistent system
for cleaning it out. You can't do it both ways.
Okay.
ולא ימחוק בבת אחת. veloy imchok bevabbat achat. ולא ימחוק בבת אחת,
veloy imchok bevabbat achat, שהמוחק בבת אחת רע למוכר. shehamochek bevabbat achat
ra lamocher. Don't go ahead and do like one quick one, quick
one, because that's not fair to the seller. Now I don't understand,
this is where the part I really couldn't understand. If you do
one quick movement, then you're not going to do such a good
job. If you're not going to do such a good job, I
would think that that's unfair to the buyer because then the container
isn't fully cleaned out and there's still residue left. So I didn't
ever... I couldn't understand from the רשב"ם Rashbam why if I don't
do as good of a job, it's bad for the seller.
You're talking about the other side of what you're doing?
Yeah, it would...
No, but we're talking about, I think the מחק, machak, the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, and this I was trying to think
about this, if we're talking about the balance, if we're talking about
the balance, I could understand it, because if you do the balance
and you're talking about the weights and you don't clean off the
weights well enough, then they weigh more than they should and it's
bad for the מוכר. mocher. But the רשב"ם Rashbam says that we're
talking about cleaning out containers, and if you're cleaning out containers and
you don't clean it out well enough and there's residue left, then
that's going to be bad for the buyer. The metal plate? What?
The metal plate? No, he says we're not talking about this anymore.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says that this issue of the מחק machak is
you have your one liter container and then when you're buying your
wine from me or whatever it is, I fill it up...
No, no, no, that's what I said. When I said the מחק
machak I said we're doing now a container. That's the way the...
if you were talking about this, I would agree, right? Then it
would depend which side or if we're talking about the weights themselves,
if they... if you haven't cleaned them well, then it's bad for
the seller. But here, when we're talking about sticking a gourd in,
I guess you could have said a gourd was cleaning out the
pans, right? So it could be that. But the רשב"ם Rashbam says
we're talking about the container and I don't... right, what? Yeah, and
I don't understand. If you're talking about the container here, if you
don't do a good job cleaning, then it's going to help the
buyer... help the seller, excuse me, help the seller. So yeah, I
agree, I wanted to read it talking about this, okay? Because anyway,
but anyway, that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam says it. I don't know
if your footnotes explain it any better. Okay, anyway, he says, so
ולא ימחוק בבת אחת, veloy imchok bevabbat achat,
don't do like a quick one in one swoop, שהמוחק בבת אחת
רע למוכר, shehamochek bevabbat achat ra lamocher, that's not fair to the
seller. Okay, again, this would make more sense if we're talking about
the pans or about the weights. ויפה ללוקח. veyafeh lalokeach. ולא ימחוק
מעט מעט, v'lo yimchok me'at me'at, don't do like really, like slowly,
slowly, whatever, and then you're gonna do it super, שרע ללוקח ויפה
למוכר, she'ra lalokeach veyofeh lamocher, that cleans it out a little bit
too well, maybe if it's like using the harsh metal, you know,
maybe you even wear away some, some degree at the container itself,
and that's bad for the buyer and good for the seller. Again,
to me it would seem the exact opposite, there's obviously something I'm
not understanding here. Okay, על כולן אמר רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Al
kulan amar Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. Anyway, we get the idea. On
all of them, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai said
all these things about indicating like you have to do this way
would be unfair, you gotta do it this way, not this way,
which רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai said about all
these things and this is a part, this is from a משנה
mishnah here in כלים. Keilim.
We started with the ברייתא, braita, but this last line is a
משנה mishnah in כלים. Keilim. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai said אוי לי אם אומר אוי לי אם לא אומר. Oy
li im omer, oy li im lo omer. Woe to me if
I tell people but what you have to be careful about, and
woe to me if I don't tell them. Why? אם אומר שמא
ילמדו הרמאין, Im omer, shema yilmedu harama'in, because if I tell people,
oh, you got to be very careful not to do it this
way, because that'll let somebody cheat. So now you're telling somebody, oh,
that's a good idea! I could cheat that way. I never thought
of that. Okay, so ואם לא אומר, v'im lo omer, but if
I don't tell people to be careful about this, שמא יאמרו הרמאין
אין תלמידי חכמים בקיאין במעשה ידינו. shema yomru harama'in ein talmidei chachamim
beki'in b'ma'asei yadeinu. Oh, look, we get away with murder, they have
no idea how we manage to cheat people. So do you publicize
the way people cheat so that people will be on their guard,
but you might be, you know, it's like the type of information
now that's available on the internet, right? Then other people can find
out about it and learn how to cheat or not. So the
גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו אמרה או לא אמרה. Iba'ya lehu, amrah
o lo amrah. So in the end, what did he do? Now
you could say the fact it's published in the משנה mishnah means
that he said it, but okay, maybe רבי Rebbi said it, but
did רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai decide to say
it? So אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק אמרה. Amar Rav Shmuel
bar Rav Yitzchak: Amrah. He did say it. ומהאי קרא אמרה, u'me'hai
kra amrah, from the following פסוק: posuk: כי ישרים דרכי ה' צדיקים
ילכו בם ופושעים יכשלו בם. ki yesharim darchei Hashem, tzaddikim yelchu vam
u'poshim yikashlu vam.
You know, you teach תורה Torah and the, you know, and the
righteous people will use it to do good, and you're not, and
you know, if people misuse it, like your responsibility is, you know,
is to spread knowledge, to teach תורה. Torah.
After we're done with the דף, daf, I'll tell you a funny
story about the פסוק.
posuk. The Lubavitcher רבי, Rebbe, he was using the internet with that
idea. Oh
yeah? Interesting. Use it for bad but we
could use it for תורה. Torah. The Lubavitcher רבי Rebbe passed away
before the internet became what it fully is in these days. I
mean, it still obviously you know that when it wasn't, didn't exist,
but it was, no no no, you might be right, but I'm
just saying it wasn't exactly what it is today. Okay, תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. לא תעשו עול במשפט במדה במשקל ובמשורה. Lo sa'asu avel
bamishpat, bamiddah, bamishkal, u'vamsurah. במדה, B'middah, זו מדת קרקע, zo midat karka,
when you're measuring land. שלא ימדוד לאחד בימות החמה ולאחד בימות הגשמים,
shelo yimdod l'echad biyemos hachamah v'la'echad biyemos hageshamim, that you don't sell
or you know, to one person in the summer and one person
in the winter. Why? Because in the winter apparently or the rainy
season, the rope is moist and it stretches more. So if you're
selling, you're measuring an acre with a rope, right, you have to
be consistent how you're doing the measurement and if you do it
different ways in order to cheat people, you know, now obviously that
would be, you know, you would be transgressing. Now תוספות Tosafot asks
an important question about all of this. If you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafot, he says, well the next, well I'll hold off
תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot is going to ask the question, I don't
understand why do you need a special פסוק posuk for this? This
is just straight לא תגזול. lo tigzol. You're just selling, you're just
cheating people. So we'll see the תוספות Tosafot in a minute. But
let's read a little bit more.
במשקל, B'mishkal, in weights, שלא יטמין משקלותיו במלח. shelo yatmin mishklosav bamelach.
Don't store them in salt. Now what's going to happen if you
store them in salt? So the, so if you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, he says, פירוש הקונטרס, perush hakuntres, מפני שהוא מכביד, mipnei shehu
machbid, it makes them, it makes them heavier. But of course the
funny thing is, you're the seller in this thing. So if they're
heavier, the buyer wins out. ואין נראה לרבינו תם, V'ein nireh l'Rabbeinu
Tam, דמשמע דבמוכר איירי, demashma d'bemocher airi, דומיא דבמשורה, dumya d'vamsurah, שלא
ירתיח. shelo yartiah. מפרש רבינו תם, Mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam, שהמלח מקל המשקלות.
shehamelach mekel hamishklos. Actually if you do it in salt, it makes
them lighter. ושאוב, V'sho'ev, because it like it draws out some of
the moisture from them and it actually makes them lighter. So that's
interesting. Okay. Were these metal, any metal weights?
I don't know why, well I don't
know
if the weights were metal, the weights might have been rock or
something. משקלות mishklos or these... No no no, the משקלות mishklos here,
right, thank you. Before the משקלות mishklos meant the pans. Here the
משקלות mishklos means, no thank you, means the actual like weights themselves.
So you're storing the weights themselves in a way in which it's
going to affect you know their actual weight. Oh
you mean the salt it corrodes it up, it absorbs
the moisture, that's the whole
point,
yeah.
Oh yeah, right right right. But it'll then it looks like it's
a pound, whatever, it will say a pound but it's not the
rock or whatever.
Yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly.
But if רש"י Rashi was still talking about the
pans, yeah, that wouldn't make sense.
Oh right, that's a good point. Oh, then the משקלות mishklos could
mean the pans and then it would then would depend which side
of the pan you're affecting, right. Okay, okay, now ובמשורה, u'vamsurah, which,
now משורה msurah is apparently a type of some type of a
volume of a liquid volume measure, שלא ירתיח. shelo yartiah. Now לא
ירתיח lo yartiah means... means without pouring in a liquid it bubbles
at the top, right, the froth. So don't pour it with the
froth, because then you're not selling the person the full amount. Now
that's actually not that the measure itself is false, but that's actually
that the way in which you're doing the measuring is not good,
so it's slightly different. Now תוספות *Tosfos* says I just want to
read this important תוספות *Tosfos*. במסורה שלא ירתיח *B'mesurah shelo yartiach*. ואם
תאמר פשיטא דגזל גמור הוא *v'im tomar pshita d'gezel gamur hu*. Of
course, you told the guy you're selling him an ounce and you
sold him half an ounce or three quarters of an ounce. Why
do you need a פסוק *pasuk*, right? And you could say that
about everything. Why do you need a פסוק *pasuk*? All this stuff,
when you do it you'll be over on גזל *gezel*. ותיפוק ליה
משום לא תגזול *v'teipuk lei mishum lo tigzol*. ויש לומר דאתא קרא
לחייב משעת הרתיחה אף על פי שעדיין לא מדד *v'yesh lomar d'asa
kra l'chayeiv m'shaat hartichah af al pi she'adayin lo madad*. If you're
already in the process of doing it and you have the froth
and you're planning on selling, even before you actually have maybe collected
the money, right. Now if obviously there's going to be some froth
and you're going to let it settle and then you're going to
pour some more. It's like when you go to get your soda
from those machines, you let it settle. That's what the Jews do,
they let it settle, they let it settle. Anyway, beer,
anyway. So, but he says you transgress before you're over on לא
תגזול *lo tigzol*, because if you have those מדות *middos*, if you
did the weighing that way, if you did the pouring that way,
even before you actually stole, you're over on, you know, and you're
over on לא תגזול *lo tigzol*. וכי האי גוונא אמרינן בריש אלו
נטרפין *v'chi hai gavna amrinan b'reish Eilu Nitrafin* I'm sorry איזהו נשך
*Eizehu Neshech* דלאו דכתיב במשקלות למה לי לטמון משקלות אבן ומלח הגזלה
מעלייא היא *d'lav d'chsiv b'mishkalos lama li litmon mishkalos even umelach hagzeilah
mealyei hi*. What do you mean? If you're using, you're creating these
unjust weights, that's real גזלה *gzeilah*. לעבור לאו משעת עשיה *laavor lav
m'shaat asiyah*. No, as soon as you create the unjust weights, you
transgress even before you've used it. Okay, let's read just one more
line in the גמרא *Gemara*, just finish this thing about the מסורה
*mesurah*. וקל וחומר מה מסורה שהיא אחד משלושים ושישה בלוג *v'kal vachomer
mah mesurah she'hi echad mishloshim v'shishah b'log*. So מסורה *mesurah* is a
tiny measure, it's one thirty-sixth of a לוג *log*. It's a very
small amount. הקפיד עליו תורה *hikpid alav Torah*, תורה *Torah* says you
have to be very careful that there shouldn't be even that small
amount of cheating. Like what is it? A few pennies' worth. Of
course, it's proportionally it might be a lot, but its absolute value
is only a few pennies' worth and the תורה *Torah* still cares.
קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, how much more so with these bigger measures
that if you cheat it'll be stealing even more from the person.
להין *l'hin*, וחצי הין *v'chatzi hin*, ושלישית הין *v'shlishis hin*, ורביעית הין
*v'reviis hin*, ולוג *v'log*, וחצי לוג *v'chatzi log*, ורביעית *v'reviis*, וחצי תומן
*v'chatzi tuman*, ועוכלא *v'uchla*. All of these are different measures. When we
pick up tomorrow, we're going to go through this list of different
measures as well and I'll detail exactly, you know, what their relative
sizes to one another. Okay, so we'll pick up with you tomorrow.